Shahzad Badar

Senior Public Awareness and Communications Specialist -USAID Chemonics

Summary

Have been working in the field of communications for the last 22 years and have worked for prestigious international organisations like the European Union, ECHO, World Vision, USAID Chemonics project in Punjab and KPK, formulating and implementing their communication strategies in Pakistan.

As Communication Manager with World Vision was responsible for setting up communication centers in Sukkhar, Muzafargarh, Peshawar and Islamabad for covering flood relief activities and dealing with emergency communications and other communication needs of international donors.

I have good experience of leading communication teams besides liaising with the local and international media to raise the corporate profile of the organizations.

Have also done media consultantcy work for PR organisations and worked as Editor production and as senior correspondent for prestigious English daily.

Experience

Communications Manager at World Vision Pakistan

April 2011 - July 2012 (1 year 4 months)

- *Responsible for formulating and implementing communication strategy and branding strategy
- *Responsible for ensuring production of success stories, pictures and interviews for reports and donors
- *Responsible for production of emergency reports and supervising communication offices based in Sukkhar,

Muzafargarh, Peshawar and Islamabad.

- *Responsible for all external and internal communications
- *Responsible for all media relations and inspecting all advocacy material
- *Responsible for improving and raising the profile of World Vision in Pakistan

1 recommendation available upon request

Senior Public Awareness and Communication Specialist / Media Advisor USAID Chemonics Project at USAID Chemonics

June 2009 - March 2011 (1 year 10 months)

Responsible for formulating Media policy with the Director Communication

Responsible for implementing media policy in Punjab and KPK

Responsible for managing media relations and dealing with crises and reputation management

Helping USAID reach it communications goals by arranging high profile interviews and events

Helping USAID build links with journalists

Responsible for producing success stories, pictures, documentaries, press releases and reports for USAID

8 recommendations available upon request

Media Advisor at Magnates

January 2007 - June 2009 (2 years 6 months)

Developing media relations and Reputation Management of Pakistan Telecom (PTCL) Ensuring positive coverage of PTCL in media and Crises Management

1 recommendation available upon request

Editor Production at Pulse Magazine

January 2007 - June 2009 (2 years 6 months)

Responsible for liaising with reporters in the four provincial bureaus for production of news stories and articles.

Responsible for supervising the entire production team for the timely production of the weekly magazine. Responsible for the layout design and editorial content of the magazine.

Responsible for representing the organisations in different foras and and liaising with diplomats and government representatives.

Media Advisor at European Union

May 2001 - December 2007 (6 years 8 months)

- 1- To formulate and implement the EU communication strategy in Pakistan besides planning its annual budget.
- 2- To provide guidance to ECHO and EU Member States in Islamabad when they asked for it and formulate communication strategies to highlight the activities of EU funded projects
- 3- Conceptualizing information activities, events and publications, including new initiatives plus liaising with the Media
- 4- Feeding media with information (Press releases + Press material) about EU-Pakistan activities to promote EU awareness and visibility
- 5-Preparing media products like magazine, FM radio programs, documentary films, newsletters, newspaper supplements and other promotional material.
- 6- Liaising with EU partners and project beneficiaries for developing a coherent visibility strategy and utilizing external communication resources for greater positive impact.

Senior Reporter at The Nation

March 1990 - December 2000 (10 years 10 months)

* First City Editor of the Nation Islamabad

Responsible for producing the city pages and editing the stories

- * As a reporter covered health and development issues for ten years
- * And also responsible for covering proceedings of the Senate and National Assembly

Languages

English(Full professional proficiency)Urdu(Professional working proficiency)Punjabi(Professional working proficiency)

Honors and Awards

UK govt scholarship

British Council September 1996

European University Peace Scholarship

Government of Austria March 2000

Scholarship for a Diploma course in International News Writing

Reuters Foundation London December 1997

Publications

News Production in Pakistani Newspapers

October 19, 1997 Authors: Shahzad Badar

Courses

Media Advisor

European Union

Media relations and Budgeting Media relations and visibility Communication strategies

Communications Manager

World Vision Pakistan

Emergency Communication

Senior Reporter

The Nation

International News Writing Reuters London

Senior Public Awareness and Communication Specialist / Media Advisor USAID Chemonics Project

USAID Chemonics

Writing for Impact

Independent Coursework

PR and Editing course Stanford University

Skills & Expertise

Media Relations

Strategic Communications

Corporate Communications

Public Relations

Internal Communications

Journalism

Proposal Writing

International Relations

Politics

Community Development

Press Releases

Newspapers

News Writing

Strategy

Newsletters

Editing

Storytelling

Policy

Publications

Government

Magazines

Education

Skill Development Council Ministry of Labor Pakistan

Certified Professional Manager in project Management, Project Management, 2008 - 2009

Grade: A

Activities and Societies: Was among the core team of the Chemonics Project in Pakistan

European University Vienna

Postgraduate courses in Peace Studies, Peace Studies and Conflict Resolution, 2000 - 2000

Grade: A

University of Westminster London

Master of Arts (M.A.), Communication and Media Studies, 1996 - 1997

University of Punjab

M.A English Literature, English Literature, 1990 - 1991

University of Hagazian Beirut

Bachelor of Science (BSc), Biology + Chemistry, 1981 - 1984

Grade: B

Activities and Societies: Member of the Bible society,

Saint Dominic's College Lisbon

O Levels Grade: B

Interests

Reading, travelling, social work,

Shahzad Badar

Senior Public Awareness and Communications Specialist -USAID Chemonics



10 people have recommended Shahzad

"Shahzad is a knowledgeable and bold person .Doesn't hesitates in saying what he thinks .Is an honest and hardworking person with vast knowledge on current affairs.He has indepth knowledge of Pakistan Pharmaceutical market .Has strong networking in Pakistan media .Also specializes in educating the media personnel on several issues.Most of all he is a straigh forward and clean man which is a rare commodity in Pakistan now a days."

— Aslam S., Product Manager / Marketing Manager / External Affairs Manager, Merck Sharp & Dohme, was with another company when working with Shahzad at World Vision Pakistan

"Shahzad have been in the field of communications for the last 20 years formulating and implementing communication strategies for international organizations like EU, ECHO, World Vision, and USAID. He was responsible for implementing the media strategy for USAID Firms Project, developing media networks in KPK, Punjab and arranging all high profile interviews and events in Islamabad and KPK. I have found him to be a hard working and dedicated professional, who can work well and deliver result in challenging work conditions."

— **Babar Malik**, BDS Specialist/Project Manager, USAID - FIRMS Project, worked with Shahzad at USAID Chemonics

"Shahzad is an exceptional individual. He is very competent and a man of principles. His strength is his "Can Do" attitude. I am yet to see a person with more connections with media than Shahzad. He can easily arrange complex media and communication tasks with ease and on time. He has handled complex assignments in challenging environment. His planning abilities and multitasking is unmatched. He is definitely an asset for any organization."

- Saleem Ahmed, Sr. Program Advisor, Chemonics International, managed Shahzad at USAID Chemonics

"I have known Shahzad Badar as a colleague for 7 years. His responsibilities included inter alia provide advice on media and public relations to the EU for its work in Pakistan. Needless to say, I found him a thorough professional with a flexible nature and eager to learn more. His inquisitive nature brushed his professionalism which is leading him in his carear development. I feel happy to write this recommendation for him."

— **Husnain Iftakhar**, *Senior Economist*, *European Union Delegation to Pakistan*, managed Shahzad indirectly at USAID Chemonics

"We have worked to gather in USAID funded project and Shehzad served as Public Awareness Specialist. Shehzad is very hard working and result oriented personal. He has very good knowledge of media, very sharp, effective in awareness campaigns for projecting the projects. He always keeps high value for profession and is very creative team player. He is great contributor for the success of projects and very articulate in his field with huge network of professionals."

- Hamid Javaid, was Shahzad's client

"Shahzad Badar is a highly qualified and capable media and communications professional. He has wide ranging experience in journalism and corporate and development communication. He is a gifted writer and applies his skills with utmost professionalism and high integrity. Shahzad's widest network of friends in the media, both nationally and internationally can prove to be an asset for any organization as he can ensure media coverage of news and events at all levels within and outside Pakistan. Shahzad is highly dedicated and committed to his work and is deeply appreciated for his most cordial and sincere approach towards his co-workers."

— **Hayya Ahmed**, *Team Leader Public Awareness*, *USAID FIRMS Project*, managed Shahzad at USAID Chemonics

"Shahzad believes in delegating. He trusts his colleagues to bring their best in the jobs assigned to them. Shahzad is an honest professional."

— **faruque malik**, *Operations Associate*, *Chemonics International*, worked with Shahzad at USAID Chemonics

"It has been thirteen years since I have known Shahzad, as both, a close friend and colleague. I was first introduced to Shahzad when I joined The Nation, Islamabad, where he was working as a senior reporter. Shahzad is one of the most disciplined and punctual person I've ever known. His ability to work efficiently under stressful conditions and nerve-wracking deadlines speaks volumes about his hard work, determination, and composed demeanor. He has demonstrated excellent leadership skills and morale. I would also like to add that, Shahzad is a compassionate human being with praiseworthy perseverance and ambition. I believe that he is an indispensable asset for any organization."

— **Sarvat Naheed H.**, *Writer/Reporter*, *Weekly Pulse*, was with another company when working with Shahzad at USAID Chemonics

"I had the good fortune of working with Mr. Shahzad Badar while I was working as CEO PACF. He is a thorough professional and expert in his field. Not only he has excellent personal communication skills but also possess the skills and experience required for working as a senior communication specialist. Being a seasoned journalist himself, he has vast linkages in the print and electronic media. These linkages are essential in successfully carrying out any commutation strategy. He has excellent analytical skills and is a fine team man capable of leading a multidisciplinary and multicultural team."

- Aftab Awan, CEO, Pakistan AIDS Control Federation, worked directly with Shahzad at World Vision

"Shahzad is a nice man and a true professional. He is absolutely a great human to work on."

 ${\bf -FAISAL~RAZA~KHAN}, Sr.~Reporter, ONLINE~NEWS$ - Inetrnational~News~Network, worked directly with Shahzad at Magnates

Contact Shahzad on LinkedIn